<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="aether_region_input_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright (C) 2024 Aether Compositor Authors

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <!-- ══════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       aether_region_input_manager_v1
       Global factory — clients bind it via wl_registry.
       ══════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <interface name="aether_region_input_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for per-surface input region declarations">
      This global interface is the entry point for the region-input protocol.
      Clients bind it via wl_registry and use it to obtain an
      aether_region_input_v1 object for any wl_surface they own.

      Through the per-surface object the client declares which axis-aligned
      rectangles within the surface should receive pointer/touch input
      ("active regions").  Any part of the surface that lies outside every
      active region is treated as a "dead zone": pointer and touch events
      that land in a dead zone pass through the surface to whatever is
      rendered beneath it, exactly as if the surface were not there.

      This protocol is the preferred alternative to the XShape / input-shape
      technique because the compositor only needs to consult a small, static
      list of rectangles at the moment an input event arrives — no continuous
      coordinate recalculation is required.

      DESIGN CONTRACT
      ───────────────
      • Default (no controller created):   whole surface receives input.
      • Controller created, no commit yet: whole surface receives input.
      • After commit() with zero regions:  whole surface is a dead zone.
      • After commit() with ≥1 region:     only those rectangles are live;
                                           the rest is dead zone.

      Coordinates are in surface-local pixels (relative to the top-left
      corner of the wl_surface).
    </description>

    <!-- ── Requests ─────────────────────────────────────────────────── -->

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager object">
        Destroys the manager.  All aether_region_input_v1 objects previously
        created by this manager remain valid.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_input_regions">
      <description summary="create an input-region controller for a surface">
        Create an aether_region_input_v1 for the given wl_surface.
        The surface must be owned by the calling client.

        It is a protocol error to create more than one
        aether_region_input_v1 for the same wl_surface while the previous
        one is still alive.
      </description>
      <arg name="id"      type="new_id" interface="aether_region_input_v1"
           summary="new input-region controller"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the surface to attach the controller to"/>
    </request>

  </interface>

  <!-- ══════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       aether_region_input_v1
       Per-surface input-region controller.
       ══════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <interface name="aether_region_input_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="input-region controller for one surface">
      Manages the set of active input rectangles attached to a single
      wl_surface.

      Changes are double-buffered:
        1. Call set_input_region() one or more times to accumulate the
           desired active rectangles in the pending list.
        2. Call clear_input_regions() at any time to wipe the pending list
           without committing.
        3. Call commit() to atomically replace the live region set with the
           current pending list.

      The compositor replies with the "committed" event once it has applied
      the new region set.  From that point forward, pointer and touch events
      that land outside every active rectangle are passed through to the
      surface stack below.

      When the surface is destroyed the controller is automatically cleaned
      up and the surface reverts to full input reception.
    </description>

    <!-- ── Enumerations ──────────────────────────────────────────────── -->

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="0"
             summary="a region_input object already exists for this surface"/>
      <entry name="bad_surface"         value="1"
             summary="the surface is not owned by this client"/>
      <entry name="bad_region"          value="2"
             summary="region has invalid dimensions (width or height must be > 0)"/>
    </enum>

    <!-- ── Requests ─────────────────────────────────────────────────── -->

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the controller and remove all regions">
        Destroys this controller.  The compositor immediately removes all
        active input regions from the surface; the surface reverts to
        receiving input across its full extent.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_input_region">
      <description summary="add an active input rectangle to the pending list">
        Append an axis-aligned rectangle to the pending input-region list.
        Pointer and touch events that land inside this rectangle will be
        delivered to the surface normally.

        Multiple calls accumulate: each call adds one rectangle.  Call
        clear_input_regions() to start over.  Takes effect on commit().

        x, y are in surface-local pixels.  width and height must be > 0;
        violating this is a protocol error (bad_region).
      </description>
      <arg name="x"      type="int" summary="x offset in surface-local pixels"/>
      <arg name="y"      type="int" summary="y offset in surface-local pixels"/>
      <arg name="width"  type="int" summary="region width  in pixels (must be > 0)"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="region height in pixels (must be > 0)"/>
    </request>

    <request name="clear_input_regions">
      <description summary="clear the pending input-region list">
        Discard all rectangles accumulated since the last commit().  After
        this call the pending list is empty.

        If commit() is called while the pending list is empty the surface
        becomes fully transparent to input (all events pass through).

        Does not affect the currently committed (live) region set.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="apply the pending region list">
        Atomically replace the live input-region set with the current pending
        list and clear the pending list.

        The compositor sends the "committed" event once the new set is in
        place.  From that moment input hit-testing uses the new list.
      </description>
    </request>

    <!-- ── Events ───────────────────────────────────────────────────── -->

    <event name="committed">
      <description summary="input regions have been applied by the compositor">
        Sent after each commit() once the compositor has installed the new
        input-region set.  The count field reports how many active rectangles
        are now live (0 means the surface is fully pass-through).

        Clients may use this as a synchronisation point before drawing.
      </description>
      <arg name="region_count" type="uint"
           summary="number of active input rectangles now in effect"/>
    </event>

  </interface>

</protocol>
